<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dauids comfort at Ziklag A plaine sermon made in time of dearth and scarcitie of corne and worke. By Robert Harris.</title>
            <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12825</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103794</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839539</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839539</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3970</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02693)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3970)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1025:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dauids comfort at Ziklag A plaine sermon made in time of dearth and scarcitie of corne and worke. By Robert Harris.</title>
                  <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Young] for Iohn Bartlet, at the gilt Cup in Cheape-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of Harris's "Six sermons never heretofore published".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3970:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DAVIDS</hi> COMFORT AT ZIKLAG A PLAINE SERMON made in time of dearth and ſcarcitie of Corne and WORKE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Harris.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for IOHN BARTLET, at the gilt Cup in Cheape-ſide 1628.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3970:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3970:2"/>
            <head>DAVIDS COMFORT AT ZIKLAG.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. SAM. 30.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And <hi>Dauid</hi> was greatly diſtreſſed, for the people ſpake of ſtoning him, becauſe the ſoule of all the people was grieued, euery man for his ſonnes, and for his daughters: but <hi>Dauid</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged himſelfe in the Lord his God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words briefly report <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> diſtreſſe at Ziklag: which diſtreſſe is firſt in groſſe ſaid to be great; and then more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, enlarged from the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and effects thereof. The cauſe (ouer and aboue his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate loſſe) is the mutinie of his owne people,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3970:3"/>who are 1. imbittered vpon the loſſe of their children, taken by the Amalekites (againſt whom their zeale ſhould haue been greater;) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon in the next place would haue ſtoned <hi>Dauid,</hi> as the authour of ſo much miſchiefe. <hi>Dauid</hi> then was in danger of his head: hee was like enough to dye by the hand of his friends, as a malefactor without tryall; and this diſtreſſes him. Now for the effects: <hi>Dauid</hi> firſt comforts and ſtayes himſelfe on God; who was able to helpe all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord; &amp; ready, being his God. Secondly, hauing comforted him ſelfe in God, hee conſults with God: where 1. the meanes on his part is mentioned, Gods own meanes: 2. the anſwer on Gods part, a direct anſwer; both for the means to be vſed, and ſucceſſe to be expected: he ſhould follow and he ſhould certainly ſpeed. Wee will not foreſtall another by any exact enquiry into the words, but acquaint you with ſome generall meditations, that haue beene to one, and may be to you, ſomewhat vſefull.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1.</note> this is in ſight: That the Lord doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſuffer his deareſt ſeruants to be greatly <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed: Men greatly beloued, as <hi>Dauid</hi> was, are many times greatly ſtraightned, as <hi>Dauid</hi> was. To proue this, were to waſte time. Firſt, ſee When they are chiefly thus diſtreſſed; ſecondly, Why: and as for kinds of diſtreſſes, we ſhall touch them in application, and ſo ſaue time. It ſhall ſuffice (for the preſent) to ſay, that Gods children drink of all waters, and haue experience of all afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3970:3"/>and that chiefly in theſe times. Firſt, when they haue left Gods counſels, and followed their owne deuices. Gods children are neuer worſe hampered, than in nets of their owne weauing: when they will be witty eyther againſt God, or without God, then they ſpinne a wofull threed, a Spiders webbe. For carnall reaſon is a very bad counſailor, and puts a man vpon euill meanes; and none can draw a good concluſion from ill premiſſes, but only God. Therfore when Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians haue loſt Gods wiſedome and his wayes, and betaken themſelues to their owne wit and wayes, they haue plunged themſelues wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. A man is ſecure and confident in his owne courſes, like a childe that leaues his fathers coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, and followes his owne; and the freſh-water ſouldier, that will be a Pilot before hee is fit for a Mariner, and thereupon runnes his ſhip vpon the ſands. Thus <hi>Ionah</hi> was greatly diſtreſſed when hee would be wiſer than God: thus <hi>Abraham</hi> greatly diſtreſſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. when he would liue by his wits: thus <hi>Dauid,</hi> he had ſo contriued it, that neyther <hi>Saul,</hi> nor <hi>Achitophell,</hi> nor any of them all ſhould touch him, and now hee is in all their dangers, vnleſſe God helpe him out. And neuer doe Gods children pleaſe themſelues greatly in their owne contriuements, but thus they ſpeed: where they expect great ſafety, they are greatly endangered; where much comfort, greatly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3970:4"/>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, when they haue receiued great bleſſings and comforts from God, then comes pride and ſecuritie, and that's a forerunner of a fall. Great mercies worke great thoughts and ſpirits in vs; and great thoughts make way for great afflictions. We will not inſtance in <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar. Dauid</hi> proſpered greatly, God had ſet him on high, made his mountaine ſtrong, his heart grew ſecure, then came trouble. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was greatly diſtreſſed, and when was it? after great deliuerances and bleſſings: <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>iah</hi> and <hi>Aſa</hi> the like. Mans heart cannot beare a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of comfort, no more than his head can a great meaſure of wine: therefore eyther God mingles their wine when they take it, or preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after; or elſe they be giddy, and muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed. Hence S. <hi>Paul</hi> after great conſolations had great temptations and afflictions; <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</note> and the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> in S. <hi>Luke</hi> is told of a ſword when of a ſonne, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 2.35.</note> that muſt through her heart as well as Chriſt through her loynes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, when they be to receiue ſome great comfort from God, when God hath ſome great employment, or preferment, or deliuerance, or conſolation in ſtore for his children, hee makes way thereto by ſome great affliction of bodie, minde, ſtate, friends &amp;c. as men lay the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very deepe when they meane to raiſe the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding very high. Thus <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was greatly diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but when? when he muſt be a Prince ſhortly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3970:4"/>after: thus <hi>Dauid</hi> greatly impoueriſhed, when? when ſhortly after he muſt come to the Crowne. Generally, as in darke nights it is darkeſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards day-breake: ſo tis with the Saints of God; the ſharpeſt fit is euer at the birth, when they bee deliuered of their ſorrow. So God makes his comforts more taſtefull and leſſe dangerfull to them; and therefore firſt mars them, then makes them; vndoes them, cruſhes them, and then rayſes them vp.</p>
            <p>Theſe be ſpeciall times: the generall ſhould haue beene firſt noted, <hi>viz.</hi> When Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren haue gotten ſome ſtocke and ſtrength; for the Lord is wiſe, and will not vſe an Iron Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to threſh out Cummin; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28.</note> hee will not lay weight vpon greene Timber, but firſt ſeaſon it, and then employ it after. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.</note> Thus while <hi>Peter</hi> was young hee walked at large, but after was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed. Thus for the When.</p>
            <p>Now Why doth God bring ſuch diſtreſſes on his? you may partly gheſſe by the When. He reſpects himſelfe, his Church, his particular children in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God gaines glory many waies by this. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1.</note> Firſt, his power is ſeene in their diſtreſſes, his loue, goodneſſe, truth, &amp;c. Then the Saints can ſay with <hi>Iob,</hi> Now mine eyes haue ſeene thee.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 42.5.</note> then not only preſent power and mercie is ſeene, but former: Wee ſee what power was vſed in preuenting miſerie, what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3970:5"/>mercie in giuing comfort.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, then God ſhall haue their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and companie. Children that care not for Parents in proſperitie, will to them in miſerie; theyle come early, come euery whit of them. <hi>Dauid</hi> could comfort himſelfe in his wiues, in his children before, but now ail are met in God; no wiſe but God, no child nor friend but God: now hee goes all one way, and now his confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and prayers bee ſuch as will ſet out God indeed; prayes more and more ſpiritually than euer, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <note place="margin">Reaſ.2.</note> God aymes at the Churches good in this. 1. whileſt ſhee is a ſpectator, ſhe layes about her in the getting and exerciſing of grace: others deepe ſorrowes makes all ſee how need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it is to get much ſaith, patience, Scriptures in a readineſſe. 2. theſe ſtirre vp to prayers, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, &amp;c. as when <hi>Peter</hi> is in Priſon, one behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, another impriſoned, they thought twas time to pray; therefore <hi>Acts</hi> 12. they ſet about it earneſtly: So for mercie, when they ſaw the Church diſtreſſed, famine comming towards her, they ſaue and lay vp, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> for Egypt. 2. when themſelues be afflicted, they helpe themſelues by the afflictions of others. Such went before mee in this affliction, and God loued them, why not, mee: Such cryed and ſped well, why not I: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. They follow the cloud, and doe not miſcarry. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3970:5"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <note place="margin">Reaſ. 3.</note> God aymes at the parties good in great diſtreſſes: hereby they are tried, humbled, haue experience of their frailties and graces. A Chriſtian knowes little of himſelfe till much diſtreſſed, neither what his weakeneſſe, not what his ſtrength in Chriſt is: hee neither ſees how poore himſelfe is, nor how great his God is. 2. hereby they are brought to receiue often ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of miſerie, death, h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll in themſelues; and tis good to taſte theſe things before we fecle them; twill empty a man of himſelfe, and make him truſt in the liuing God; twill learne him thoſe three Leſſons of Chriſtianitie, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath clapt vp in one verſe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. i. to worſhip God ſpiritually, to make Chriſt his iov, to lay down all confidence in the fleſh: and 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. hereby they are made helpefull to others. There is little to bee expected from man till deepely plunged. 1. Hee cannot pity others till experience hath taught him. 2. he will not be ſeruiceable till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions haue humbled and broken him. 3. hee knowes not how to comfort others till himſelfe hath beene wounded and healed. But when hee hath learned by experience, he can make his own plaiſter ſerue another man, and comfort him in the ſame affliction with the ſame conſolation. And thoſe bee the ſweeteſt and ſureſt comforts, when a man can ſay, my caſe was iuſt the ſame, &amp; here is the ſcripture, the medicine that wrought the cure in me. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3970:6"/>
            <p>Firſt for the wicked: <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> leaue them but theſe Scriptures to thinke vpon. If this bee done to the greene Tree, what ſhall bee done to the dry? If God beginne with the people that call vpon his Name, what ſhall the end of the enemies be? Are there not ſtrong plagues for the workers of Iniquitie, <hi>Iob</hi> 31? ſhall not they be diſtreſſed?</p>
            <p n="2">2 The chief Vſe is to Saints: Let not them queſtion their ſonneſhip becauſe of afflictions. In this nonage the Heire differs little from a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant: You can make no certaine Concluſion from outward things: doe not offer it, vnleſſe you will wrong God, Chriſt, the Generation of the Iuſt, your owne ſoules, all at once.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But what ſhall bee ſaid to extraordinary afflictions?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. If ſuch, God hath determined the caſe in <hi>Iob,</hi> againſt thoſe diſputants: They are no good proofes of a bad perſon or condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. But ours be not extraordinary, nothing hath befallen vs, but what is humane.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> No? when did you heare of ſuch a dearth as is now vpon vs? <hi>Anſ.</hi> When? why when an Aſſes head was worth foure pound, 2 <hi>King. 6.</hi> Therefore infer nothing againſt the truth of our Church from thence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but would the lining God ſo affict me if his Child?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> So: how?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> O I am croſſed in a childe as no man was ſo vngratefull, ſo vnnaturall.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3970:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, except <hi>David, Ely,</hi> and yet thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but I haue ſuch a beaſt to my husband as no woman euer had.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, <hi>Abigaell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but my eſtate is broken all to pieces, I am nothing worth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So was <hi>Dauid</hi> at Ziklag: ſo <hi>Naomie:</hi> and yet beloued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but I haue ſold all, and now want bread.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So the Widow of Sarepta, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4. <hi>Neh.</hi> 5. <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. and yet beloued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but my bodie is ſmitten too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So <hi>Dauids</hi> &amp; <hi>Iobs,</hi> &amp; yet beloued of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but my ſpirit is wounded, I am ſcorcht with the flames of hell, and feele it in my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But I am diſabled from all ſeruice, I can neither pray, nor read, nor heare, nor liue, not dye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So the Saints, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. the Church in <hi>Eſay;</hi> and yet beloued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but I am torne to pieces with helliſh blaſphemous Temptations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Chriſt had ſuch offered outwardly, yet beloued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But I am haled with luſts, now impure luſts, now couetous luſts, reuengefull luſts, and they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3970:7"/>make me weary of my life. So <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. yet beloued. What then is to be reſolued vpon? Surely, that neither things preſent, nor things to come, ſhal euer ſeparate vs from the loue of God; for no afflictions forfeit our Title.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but mine be fins, paſſions, temptations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Let them bee what they will be; if they be afflictions to vs; if they tire vs, wound vs, make vs cry to God, as <hi>Ichoſaphat</hi> did, when they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue vs, they weaken not our Title. Oh but that the ſmart of them may do without the hatred of ſin: they may weary men becauſe painefull, not becauſe ſinfull. They may; but marke, 1. theſe two be not well oppoſed: often the painefulneſs comes from the ſinfulneſſe; were they not ſinful, wee could brooke them well enough for their pleaſure and profit. 2. if oppoſed, paine in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites only followes ſins committed. Thou art diſtreſſed before hand, and in great feare leſt thou ſhouldſt commit it; as <hi>Paul,</hi> Who ſhall deliuer me from the bodie of death? 2. great ſinnes are painefull onely, if nothing but paine bee heeded. Thou art troubled with the firſt motions, a whole bodie of ſinne. 3. ſinne is only painefull to the vnſanctified. Thou art troubled as much for want of faith, loue, humilitie, thankefulneſſe, as for the ouerflowing of ſinne. 4. paine makes one howle, but not to God, at leaſt in the firſt place. But ſinne driues a <hi>Dauid</hi> firſt to God, then to men; ends in prayer, &amp; not in chaſing deſpaire.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3970:7"/>And is it thus with thee? either condemne <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> or ſay, a man may be croſſed in wife, childe, houſe, goods, friends, kinſmen, all at once; nay hazzarded in his life, tempted in his ſoule, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in his conſcience plunged into a ſea of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and yet be deare to God; a bleſſed man, a glorious Chriſtian. witneſſe <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, <note place="margin">Doct.</note> they thinke and ſpeake of ſtoning <hi>Dauid.</hi> See our nature; In croſſes wee are apt to flye vpon men, rather than to fall down and humble our ſelues before God. Thus, were the Iſraelites croſſed? they murmure at <hi>Moſes,</hi> and they will ſtone him. Want they wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? ſtone <hi>Moſes:</hi> Want they meate? ſtone <hi>Moſes.</hi> And thus the King of Iſrael at Samaria, <hi>Abab</hi> for <hi>Eliah, &amp;c.</hi> Nay wee ſee this diſeaſe too ſtrong in Saints: <hi>Sarah,</hi> in the 16. of <hi>Geneſis, Aſa &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. The reaſon is cleere: firſt, wee ſtoope not to God, becauſe wee are naturally emptie of Faith: wee cannot ſee him, wanting an eye thats ſpirituall: wee will not, becauſe wee expect no helpe from him; and it is Faith that makes vs ſtoope, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Wee chafe at man, becauſe proude; and therefore fretfull and complayning: 2. guile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and therefore rather tranſlate than confeſſe our faults; like children, that will rather quarrell with ſeruants for complayning, than themſelues for offending.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3970:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. Feare this diſtemper in nature, and watch which way our hearts are working in the day of affliction. Vnleſſe the croſſe bee verie immediate, our hearts breake out towards men rather than God; and wee ſooner fret, chafe, threaten, curſe, than confeſſe, pray, ſubmit: &amp; this is a fearefull ſinne, beware of it. And now lets not ſpeake in the language of the wicked; Tis long of <hi>Dauid,</hi> therefore ſtone him: tis long of Corne-maſters who hold-in corne, that theres ſuch ſcarcitie, therefore downe with them: tis long of Incloſers, therefore downe with them: tis long of hard Land-lords, and therefore down with them, long of Merchants that tranſport: tis long of ſome mens pride, others waſtfulneſſe, others wantonneſſe; and ſo grow bitter againſt others: But ſay, tis long of mee and my fathers houſe; my ſinnes haue encreaſed wrath vpon Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; I haue beene proude, wanton, waſtefull, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed plenty, murmured &amp;c. I haue ſinned the ſinnes of others, in that I haue ſpoken of them with more delight than griefe, in that I haue not wept for them, ſtood in the gap; otherwiſe God would neuer beate anothers ſinnes on my backe. Thus lets doe, fret at our owne ſinnes, befoole our ſelues; and not onely ſo, but in ſtead of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing at men, caſt downe our ſelues before God, ſee the rod, and God appointing it: that done, goe to God as <hi>Dauid</hi> doth, goe by faith, goe in the workes of repentance, goe for counſaile; lye
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3970:8"/>at his foote, ſaying, Lord wee yeeld, wee yeeld: if thou wilt haue vs poore, wee will be poore; if thou wilt haue our goods, houſes, habitations, here we are, and we reſigne that which wee haue forfeited a thouſand times: This the onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy theres left vs. We muſt not ſpend our time in inueighing againſt others, but in accuſing our ſelues: wee muſt not imbitter our hearts, by dwelling vpon the inſtruments, but humble them by looking vp to God, and huſh them by a free ſubmiſſion or our ſelues. Fretting doth but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our miſerie, ſubiection and yeeldance only eaſeth vs; and therefore ſay as they, <hi>Lamen.</hi> 3. 22.—40.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Comfort, if ſtormes doe not breed thiſtles and nettles in our ground: Comfort, if croſſes do not draw paſsions, oathes, curſes, repinings, ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, but prayers, confeſsions &amp;c. from vs. O tis well when being let bloud, our veynes ſend out that which is pure, not now that which is blacke, poy ſoned: This argues a good conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea the finger of God; for croſſes of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are not ſo much as purgatiue, much leſſe alteratiue: Tis grace that changes our complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and tis as good a ſigne when croſſes take well, as when the Word doth. If then wee finde that our croſſes ſend vs homeward, ſet vs againſt our ſinnes, make vs cry out, becauſe wee can forgiue no more, beare no more, becauſe wee bee ſo full of wrath, paſsion &amp;c. lets bleſſe God for this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3970:9"/>cure: for nature chafes, moralitie bites it in; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſanctitie makes ſinne odious, ſtirres vp deſires of grace, puls downe fleſh, ſets vp God in Chriſt; in ſhort, improues the croſſe.</p>
            <p>Followeth, <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
               <hi>Their ſoules are bitter for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> ſo the childes miſerie is the parents bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Tis gall and wormwood to a parent to ſee his ſonnes and daughters deliuered to miſerie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> If there be grace in the parent, then the parent ſees his owne ſinne in the childes ſmart: It grieues a good man to ſee a beaſt, a ſtranger bleed for him, much more his childe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If but nature, yet nature is ſtrong in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that hath ſo mingled fathers and children, that in one both are ſinitten; both bleed and ſmart, both liue and dye together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. For vngratefull children: Think of this; your ſorrowes are your parents forrowes, your ſhame theirs, your paine theirs, your loſſe theirs; and if you loue not your ſelues, loue your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: kill not them by your wickedneſſe, fill not their ſoules with gall who haue fed you with milke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Againſt thoſe that robbe and ſpoile, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, defraud and beggar yongue and old, the mother and the childe vpon her: Oh tis a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſin to ruine houſes and townes, to lay whole families on heapes, to ſet father, mother, ſonne, daughter all on weeping; the crye of ſo manie will ſurely to heauen, the ſmart of ſo many will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3970:9"/>deeply imbitter; when children ſhall crye to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents for bread and they haue it not, when they ſhall call for portions and they haue none, for coates and they haue none, food and money and they haue none, when they ſhall looke one way on the miſeries of their children, another way on the vniuſtice, vnmercifulneſſe, oppreſſion of Land-lords, of Creditors, and ſee themſelues and theirs for euer betrayed to miſery through the default of others; Oh this fills the heart with many a bitter thought, the mouth with many a bitter curſe; the father curſes, the mother curſes, the ſonne curſes, the daughter curſes; they lye at God, and giue him no reſt till hee reuenge them vpon ſuch hurtfull perſons: and that God that would not haue a bird killed from her yongue, will heare theſe curſes, and make the earth, and ſtones, and walls of mens houſes, and lands to feele them: Oh then doe not robbe, kill, cruſh mens ſonnes and daughters, this will worke bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe in others, to vs, to ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. For inſtruction to vs all: Is it ſo bitter to ſee our children in miſery, captiuity? then meete the Lord before ſentence goes forth, leſt our ſoules be made bitter for our ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: ſhould the Lord ſend the ſword amongſt vs to our Ziklags, and wee ſhould ſee our daughters rauiſhed, our ſonnes butchered before our eyes, would not this bee bitter? Should wee ſee ones legge off, a ſeconds arme, a thirds head, a fourth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3970:10"/>crying to vs, hanging on vs, would not this bee bitter? ſhould wee ſee the Amalekites in our land, our children carried away for ſlaues, would not this be bitter? ſhould our children fall in the ſtreets for bread, dye for thirſt, they ready to eat vp vs, we ready to chop them to the pot, would not this bee bitter? Oh how could our eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold theſe things, how could our ſoules digeſt ſo great bitterneſſe? Oh lets now preuent this, that we may neuer ſee or feele it: Tell mee not, theres no danger: the Word of God is agaiuſt vs; moſt of thoſe ſinnes which haue brought Captiuitie, Sword, Famine vpon others, are amongſt vs: wee ſee the Lord hath begunne already, and our brethren haue begun to vs in this bitter cup. O the bitter lamentations in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; fathers, mothers weeping for their ſonnes that bee not: Oh England, looke to it that wee drinke not vp the dregges; Oh that thou wouldſt faſt and mourne in publicke; Oh that you would each in priuate. Here each man wept bitterly for his ſonnes and daughters, but it was too late, they were gone: Nay, twas not too late; though gone, teares will waft them home againe: thoſe teares that will recouer chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, will continue children; therefore each man for himſelfe, for his ſonnes, weepe apart, pray, faſt, mourne, wiues apart, husbands apart, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren apart; ſtand before the Lord as <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> did with your little ones, and ſay, Oh Lord ſpare
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3970:10"/>our Ziklags, our houſes, our ſons, our daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſpare them from the ſword, from famine, from peſtilence, from miſery and who knowes but that the Lord may yet haue mercie?</p>
            <p>He comforted himſelfe (or, ſtrengthened, all is one) for the ioy of the Lord is ſtrong.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The world is neuer ſo empty of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts but that comfort may be found in God: though there be ſomewhat a dearth of comfort in the earth, yet Gods houſe is euer filled; in heauen comfort is to bee had when none in earth, in God when none in creatures. <hi>Daniel, Dauid, Paul;</hi> thouſands would witneſſe this if needefull.</p>
            <p>The inſtance is plaine: when <hi>Dauid</hi> could not comfort himſelfe in his wiues, nor his children, nor his goods, nor in any thing vnder the Sunne, he could in ſomething aboue the Sunne, &amp;c. And the Reaſon is at hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 1. God is the God of all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Spring of comfort; if any water tis in the Sea, if any light tis in the Sunne, if any comfort tis in God, there it reſts, there tis when no where elſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God is Al-ſufficient; there the heart finds euery want ſupplyed, euery good thing lodged: if the diſcouragement grow from wants, want of power, want of wiſedome, of comfort, of helpe, there the heart receiues anſwer; in God
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3970:11"/>there is enough; there tis to bee had, and that freely. As God is Al-ſufficient to furniſh vs with all neceſſaries, ſo infinite in power, wiſedome, goodneſſe, to helpe vs againſt all euils, feared or felt. It our diſcouragement grow from euils feared, looke vp to him and he can preuent all, as you ſee in <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Eſters</hi> ſtory, and <hi>Paul: Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was neere to killing when <hi>Saul</hi> was now rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to chop vpon him; the Church in <hi>Eſter</hi> was at a low ebbe, when the lot was caſt; <hi>Paul,</hi> when forty had vowed his death; <hi>Peter,</hi> when the next day he muſt dye, and but one night, houre, ſtep betweene death and him, yet reſcued.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If afflictions haue ouertaken vs and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged vs, looke vp againe, and ſee how eaſily the Lord can take them off: this weeke <hi>Dauid</hi> hath neither wife, nor childe, nor corne, nor cattell, and by the next he hath his owne, and a great deale more: this yeare you ſee hee is worſe than nought for wealth, the next a King; yea <hi>Peter</hi> can tell you, that impriſonment may be for a night, deliuerance ere morning; <hi>Dauids</hi> heauineſſe may be your gueſt this night, ioy to morrow, <hi>Pſal. 30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If afflictions bee long and ſtrong, and thence diſcouragement, looke vp againe and you ſhall finde, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that after two dayes God will reuiue you, and you ſhall liue in his ſight. Hee can heale old wounds in a ſhort ſpace; as in the captiuity, <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.5.</note> in the man in the Goſpell; and deepe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3970:11"/>wounds with a little tent. When <hi>Dauid</hi> is broken all to pieces, his eſtate to pieces, his houſhold, his army, his heart (they had wept till wearie of weeping) Loe in two or three dayes he can make vp all againe.</p>
            <p n="4">4 If afflictions bee moſt bi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter, and ſtinging, and laſting to our end, and therefore diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; looke vp, and ſee, and God can ouer-top all theſe ſorrowes with comfort, and ſweeten the bittereſt cup: why hee hath more conſolations than there bee afflictions: as one abounds ſo the other. Hee hath ſtronger conſolations than affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, hee can make a <hi>Dauid</hi> for the preſent ſay <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.19. and for the time paſt, Tis good I haue beene afflicted; and for the future, <note place="margin">Iſah. 119. &amp; 73.</note> Thou wilt bee my guide to the death, and ſo receiue mee to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: yea hee can make a <hi>Peter</hi> ſleepe in irons, a <hi>Paul</hi> ſing in dungeons, <note place="margin">Act. 12 &amp; 16.</note> a Marty reioyce in ſufferings, <hi>Heb</hi> 10. Why then if in God may euer bee found that which will anſwer our wants, ſupply all our griefes, theres comfort ſtill to be had.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> Now then (Brethren) is not this God worth the hauing? You cannot alwaies haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in wealth, comfort in health, comfort in neighbors, in children, in wiues, theſe be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies: theſe, while they be, doe ſometime mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter matter of griefe; yea, ſometime their life &amp; preſence doth diſcourage: <note place="margin">Eſay 20</note> but in IEHOVA is conſtant peace, conſtant comfort, and ioy to bee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3970:12"/>found; He is conſtantly good, great, true, &amp;c. Oh get him; how euer you doe, get him, and you haue all; come what will come, he changes not, his comforts are ſure; neuer ceaſe ſeeking, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, hearing, conferring, till his Image bee ſet vpon you, and your hearts aſſured of his loue. You haue ſeene the comforts of the world, you ſee how all ciſternes faile you, goe to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, in the word of God, in the houſe of God, in the fauour of God, you ſhall haue comfort, in his light you ſhall ſee light, when others nothing but darkeneſſe round about. Oh then, thou that ſitteſt in darkeneſſe, in the darkeneſſe of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the darkeneſſe of ſinne, in the darkeneſſe of affliction, darkeneſſe of pouertie, debt; thou that ſeeſt no light, none within thee, none with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, none in thy ſoule, none in thy minde, none in thine eſtate, friends, &amp;c. ariſe, put on beautie, come into the light, ſtand vp from the dead, (dead comforts, dead companions, dead workes) and the LORD ſhall giue thee life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For Saints: why doe not they chide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, and call vpon themſelues for comfort? Surely, Ioy is comely; and it is their part to reioyce in God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but how can wee in ſad times, in the middeſt of ſorrow?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> How did the Apoſtles? they reioyced in the ſtocks.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3970:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> True in caſe of perſecution: but how ſhould we in affliction?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> How doth <hi>Dauid?</hi> he had loſt wife, child, all, yet hee comforts himſelfe; in what? when all was gone? in God, in him was all; &amp; ſo long as God ſtood to him, all ſtaide with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But what if ſinne haue haled afflictions on vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Dauid</hi> was not cleere, yet in God is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort then; comfort, becauſe hee is gracious and ready to pardon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Yea, but what if the miſerie be common, not particular and perſonall?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Such was <hi>Dauids,</hi> yet hee comforts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Why God can heale a Towne as ſoone as a man; a Shire as ſoone as a Towne; a Kingdome as ſoone as a Shire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Yea, but what if ones eaſe be deſpemte?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So was <hi>Dauids</hi> to mens iudgements: houſes burnt, goods gone, the enemie was gotten into poſſeſſion; and yet <hi>Dauid</hi> comforts him ſelfe in God. And in truth, ther's no mane caſe, eſtate, ſoule, deſperate to God: if wee were nothing, hee could make vs ſomething, if worſe than no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, he could repaire vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Yea, but what if nothing left?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yet if God loft, all is well, all is in him; all power, all wiſedom all wealth, comfort, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But the times <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> exceeding hard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But God is as kinde, as rich as euer; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3970:13"/>as full, grace and comfort as cheape.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But when pouertie pinches, neede preſſes: what comfort then?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, the conſolations of God are ſtrong: thoſe croſſes that ſeeme to ſwallow you, ſhall be very ſufferable, if you flye to him. Oh then flye to him by faith, <note place="margin">Hab. 3.</note> ſay as <hi>Hab. vlt. Though the Figge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, &amp;c. yet will I reioyce in the Lord.</hi> Flye by Prayer; and one faithfull Prayer will ſhake off theſe yokes as eaſily as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did his bonds. Flye to the Word, &amp; ſome <hi>Tychieus</hi> will comfort your hearts as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. Some one promiſe or other will ſettle you beyond expectation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but what if God himſelfe be a terror, not a comfort?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The word ſpeaketh bloud not peace; yet reconcile thy ſelfe to God, caſt out ſinne, caſt thy ſelfe vpon his mercue: ſay, If any mercie or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the world, tis in God; therefore to him Ile goe, there Ile lye at his gate, though hee kill me, Ile truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But what if I haue done ſo, and yet finde no comfort?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Waite, <note place="margin">Pſal. 85.8.</note> hearken, for the Lord will ſpeake peace to his, &amp;c. He that truſted in him never was aſhamed. Heare then thou that lookeſt into thy barne, and ther's no comfort, corne is gone; into thy purſe, ther's no com<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, mony is gone; into thy cupboard, ther's no comfort, bread is gone; vnto thy children, ther's no comfort, thy owne
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3970:13"/>fleſh and bone is gone; into thy heart, and ther's no comfort, hope and ioy is gone; vnto thy friends and land, and behold darkeneſſe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Eſay 5,</hi> the laſt verſe. yet looke vpward to heauen, there comfort growes; to Chriſt, ther's comfort treaſured; to God, and there the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is as full as euer; conclude, God is mine, and therefore comfort is mine; hee is comfort with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bread, without friends, without life.</p>
            <p>Next, <hi>Dauid</hi> conſults with God in time of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> Wee muſt not ſpend time in whyning, fretting, muſing; but wee muſt conſult, and caſt whats beſt to be done: The people doe the one, <hi>Dauid</hi> the other. So <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 42.1. <note place="margin">Exod. 10.7.1. Sam. 6.2.</note> So the Egyptians to <hi>Pharaoth:</hi> the Philiſtims in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel:</hi> And <hi>Ephraims</hi> folly is herein taxed, that hee would ſtand ſtill at the birth, <hi>Heſ</hi> 13.13. But I preſſe not this; onely for Vſe thus much.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> We are in <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtraight (in a ſenſe:) the people weep till they can weep no more, their ſoules be bitter for ſonnes and daughters, yea too many ſpeake almoſt of ſtoning euery <hi>Dauid,</hi> whom they conceiue to bee an occaſion of their miſery: What muſt wee doe? ſurely <hi>Dauid</hi> is a good patterne; 1. he comforts himſelfe in God, ſo muſt we, elſe our who bee not our owne, nor graces, wee can neither ſpeake to God nor man; diſcouragement robbes a man of all: 2. <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3970:14"/>goes to Gods ordinances, Gods word, Gods mouth, askes Gods aduice; ſo muſt wee, heare what God ſaith, what he calls for; and hee calls for more faſting, ſubmiſſion; calls vs from our feaſts, faſhions, laces, &amp;c. 3. <hi>David</hi> forthwith executes what God ſpeakes, ſo muſt wee; you haue beene told that this expence in feaſting, in building, in houſhould-ſtuffe, brauery for your ſelues and children, abuſe of plenty would beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar you; beleeue it now, confeſſe, amend it: and we tell you now, you muſt ſtoope that are poore, you muſt helpe that are rich, doe it, &amp;c. But if wee ſhould now, it were too late. No, God can fetch Ziklag againe when tis gone, if ſought vnto: But what may bee done: You have heard (Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) tis not in vain to ſeck to God 12. ſeek to God with teares, faſtings, out with your ſins, downe with your hearts, yeeld, yeeld, and acknowledge abuſe of plentie: 3. vſe policie, and prouide as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, worke, the maine defect is from want of worke: tis in vaine to ſpeake of bringing downe ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vnleſſe there bee employment. Were barley <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhillings, if men have not worke tis all one: therefore you poore bee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to worke for bread, you rich ſtudy to ſinde worke; tis impoſſible to employ all: thus do, you that have money <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (out of feares) hoard it, produce, employ it, and bring not certaine miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes vpon vncertaine <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: a. you that haue wool, hemp, &amp;c. now ſet it <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. 3. you that haue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3970:14"/>land, loue tillage; men may diſcourſe, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tillage ſuch a land as this cannot ſtand: loue houſe-keeping; tis better keepe men as ſeruants, rather than as rogues, as maſters: 4. you that haue meanes without land, helpe to ſowe the land that this year will lye vntilled and vnſowne, without helpe, and make ſome bargaine with poor men, &amp;c. Why but there is not employment for halfe. Yet againe: Why but theres no mony, theres little. Yet there might be more, if pride in lace, plate, &amp;c. might downe, if vnbeliefe did not beare the keyes of their coffers that haue manie houſes. Suppoſe there were leſſe mony, pay men in corne, bread, cloth, &amp;c. But theres no worke: No, looke to your fields, were ditches ſcoured, mariſhes drained, lands ploughed in many fields, it would quite coſt: looke to your high wayes, all the poore in the Countrey bee ſcarce crow to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and lay ſtones in them for ſome weekes, &amp;c. But we have not to pay them. I anſwer once for all, better keepe them working than begging and wandring: kept they muſt be, and if they catch a haunt of idling and roguing, theyle bee paſt all ſhame, all worke, all thrift, all grace, and we ſhall all rue it: Therfore if you know better means, vſe them, and ſet your wits on worke that ſomething may be done, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3970:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3970:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
